Konvitz, Milton R. Additional Papers /4039 B
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Milton R. Konvitz Additional Papers
1936-1986
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Konvitz, Milton R.
/4039 B
6.33 cubic feet
6.3 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
7952321
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, November 18, 2013
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, September 23, 2016
Biographical / Historical
March 12, 1908-September 5, 2003 Milton Konvitz, a Cornell University faculty member and authority on constitutional and labor law, and civil and human rights, died Sept. 5 at the age of 95. Konvitz was a founding faculty member in the School of Industrial and Labor Relations from 1946 until his retirement in 1973. He was also a professor in Cornell's Law School. Konvitz is perhaps best known for his American Ideals course, which he taught to more than 8,000 students over the course of his career, never giving the same lecture twice. "I saw the U.S. Constitution as it has been interpreted as a magnificent depository of our ideals, both individual and social," he said. His course exposed students to the great intellectual thinkers and philosophers throughout history whose writings had shaped those ideals. They included Sophocles, whose play Antigone is Cornell's New Student Reading Project this year. One student he influenced was U.S. Supreme Court Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg, Cornell Class of 1954, who considers him a mentor. At Cornell Konvitz also was a founder of the university's Department of Near Eastern Studies and Program of Jewish Studies. "I felt it was essential for a college interested in the humanities not to leave out Hebrew language and literature," he said. "And the knowledge of Jewish history, which began 4,000 years ago and has contributed to civilization no less than Greek, Roman or English history, is important to today's students-Jewish and non-Jewish." He often hosted students at his Ithaca home and helped start the first Kosher dining option at Cornell, Young Israel House. In addition, for nearly 30 years he directed the Liberian Codification Project, which drew up the official body of statutory laws that is still in force in the Republic of Liberia today, despite the current political upheaval there. Konvitz also edited the opinions of Liberia's Supreme Court and received the Grand Band of the Order of the Star of Africa, the highest award given to foreigners, as well as an honorary degree from the University of Liberia, one of seven honorary degrees he received in his lifetime. Active as a scholar and writer until his death, he wrote books and articles on American constitutional law that won him wide recognition and were cited in U.S. Supreme Court opinions. Among his nine books is Fundamental Liberties of a Free People: Religion, Speech, Press, Assembly, which was republished earlier this year with an expanded introduction by him that is strongly critical of the Rehnquist Supreme Court. Other books include A Century of Civil Rights (1983) and Judaism and Human Rights (2nd ed. 2001). He also edited a dozen volumes, including two on American philosopher Ralph Waldo Emerson, whose thinking shaped his views. One Emersonian idea he absorbed was that readers give life to books, which Konvitz recast as follows: "It is in their hearing that students bring life to the words, the thoughts, the teacher." Konvitz was born in Safed, Palestine (now Israel ), in 1908, the son of a rabbi. He immigrated to the United States in 1915 and became a naturalized citizen in 1926. He received a bachelor's degree in 1929 and a law degree in 1930, both from New York University, and a Ph.D. in philosophy from Cornell in 1933. Before joining Cornell's faculty, he was one of three assistant general counsels to Thurgood Marshall at the NAACP Legal Defense Fund for three years. He is survived by his wife, Mary, of Oakhurst, N.J.; a brother, Phillip, of Elberon, N.J.; a son and daughter-in- law, Josef and Isa, of Paris, France; and two grandsons, Eli and Ezra. Josef Konvitz, who grew up in Ithaca, is now an official at the Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /3033: Milton R. Konvitz Liberian Project Files /4039: Milton R. Konvitz Papers /4039 AV: Milton R. Konvitz American Ideals Lectures Audio-Visual Materials /4039 a: Milton R. Konvitz Papers Guide (Volume 1). Laser Copy /4039 L: Milton R. Konvitz Liberian Codification Project /4085: Milton R. Konvitz Additional Papers /4220m: Milton Konvitz Additional Papers /4289 AV: ILR School Alumni Affairs and Development Audio-Visual Materials /4297: ILR School Biography Files 6047: Archives Information File
Konvitz, Milton R.(Milton Ridvas), 1908-2003
7952321
- Whole file folders of newspaper clippings removed from Subject file series as per RS instructions (Box 1)
  - Folder A, Correspondence of Rabbi Jacob B Agus, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Has English and Hebrew
  - Folder B, Primarily the Correspondence of Professor Konvitz, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Folder C, Correspondence of Professor Konvitz, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Folder D, Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings, Professor Konvitz, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Folder E, Correspondence of Professor Konvitz, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Folder F, Correspondence of Professor Konvitz and Papers, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Free Inquiry: Why I am a Jew", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Newspaper clipping and correspondence
  - Folder G, Envelopes of Professor Konvitz, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Folder G, Correspondence of Professor Konvitz and Miscellaneous Papers, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sidney Goldmann, Correspondence, Obituary, and Profile, 1974-1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Folder G, Correspondence of Professor Konvitz, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Folder H, Professor Konvitz Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Folder H, Papers and Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Folder I-J, Hebrew Culture Foundation and Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Professor Konvitz, "Hakhanah", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    July 1984
  - Folder I-J, Correspondence of Milton Konvitz, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Folder I-J, Correspondence of Milton Konvitz and "A Century of Achievement" Booklet, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    In English and Hebrew
  - Pamphlets for "Jewish Academy of Arts and Sciences" and Biographies, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    In Hebrew and English
  - The Journal of Law and Religion Documents, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Whole file folders of newspaper clippings removed from Subject file series as per RS instructions (Box 2)
  - Folder K, Correspondence and Biography of Horace Kallen, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Folder K, Correspondence of Professor Konvitz, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Biography and Publications of Max Kampelman, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Folder L, Correspondence of Professor Konvitz, Paper by Beryl Levy, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Folder M, Correspondence and Miscellaneous Writing, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Midstream: A Monthly Jewish Review" Documents and Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Folder M, Correspondence of Professor Konvitz, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence of Shirley McClintock, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Folder N, Correspondence, Royalty Statements, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Folder O, Correspondence, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Essays in Honor of Leo Pfeffer Paper, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Folder P, Correspondence, Royalty Statements, Miscellaneous Papers, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Folder R, Correspondence, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Folder R, Correspondence and Book Reviews, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Folder S, Correspondence and the Smilen Literary Award, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Folder S, Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Folder S, Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Folder T-U, Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Folder W, Correspondence, Guide to American Law, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Folder X-Y-Z, Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Whole file folders of newspaper clippings removed from Subject file series as per RS instructions (Box 3)
  - School of Industrial and Labor Relations Documents, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Regarding Forest Home, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Docum Center and Correspondence regarding the Milton Konvitz Papers, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and Writings of Professor Konvitz, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Cornell Inquiry and Writing by Konvitz, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Cornell/ILR Correspondence, Correspondence with Glen Faber, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Cornell/ILR Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Cornell/ILR Correspondence, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Cornell/ILR Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Cornell/ILR Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Legacy of Horace M Kallen, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence of Professor Konvitz, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Council on Religion and Law Documents, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Evaluation of a Research Proposal to the National Endowment for the Humanities, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Alan Dershowitz, Biographies and Newspaper Clippings, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Newsletters, etc., 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Whole file folders of newspaper clippings removed from Subject file series as per RS instructions (Box 4)
  - ACLU Papers, 1982-1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - ACLU Papers, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - ACLU Papers, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - ACLU Papers, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - ACLU Papers, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - ACLU Papers, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - ACLU Papers, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - ACLU Papers, 1943-1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Anti-Defamation League Papers, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Anti-Defamation League Papers, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Whole file folders of newspaper clippings removed from Subject file series as per RS instructions (Box 5)
  - Council of Europe Press Releases, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    In English and French
  - Council of Europe Press Releases, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Council of Europe Press Release, Directorate of Press and Information, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    English and French
  - Council of Europe Press Releases, 1980-1982 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Council of Europe, Collection of Decisions of the European Commission of Human Rights, 1960-1963 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    French and English
  - Council of Europe, Collection of Decisions of the European Commission of Human Rights, 1960-1962 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Recent accession from MK of current newsletters, etc. (Box 6)
  - Legalization of Bingo in New York City, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    August 8 1958
  - Bilingual Rights and Issues Newspaper Clippings, 1973-1980 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Confirmation of Judge John Bigelow, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - African American and Jewish Rights and Issues, 1971-1979 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Birth Control Legality and Religious Opposition Newspaper Clippings, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - The Bible and Prayer Newspaper Clippings, 1961-1963 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - The Bible and Love Newspaper Clippings, 1955-1957 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    English and Hebrew
  - Beggars in New York Newspaper Clipping, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Father Berrigan Newspaper Clippings, 1970-1973 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - The Allan Bakke Case Newspaper Clippings, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - The Bible Newspaper Clippings, 1952-1973 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings on Bail, 1951-1974 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Backlash Newspaper Clippings, 1966-1969 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Automobile Newspaper Clippings, 1950-1967 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Automation Newspaper Clippings, 1955-1968 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - The Arts Newspaper Clippings, 1965-1980 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Army Segregation Newspaper Clippings, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Artificial Insemination on Humans Newspaper Clippings, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Arbitration Newspaper Clippings, 1968-1983 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Association: NAACP Newspaper Clippings, 1958-1964 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Rights to Asylum Newspaper Clippings, 1950-1966 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Athens Newspaper Clipping, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Attica Incident Newspaper Clippings, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Australia Newspaper Clippings, 1948-1951 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Arrest and Records Newspaper Clippings, 1962-1973 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Arts and State Aid Newspaper Clippings, 1961-1969 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Annual Wage Articles, 1961-1966 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Arms Newspaper Clippings, 1963-1977 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Newspaper Clippings Regarding Arabs, 1964-1970 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Anti-Trust Laws Newspaper Articles, 1947-1964 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Appalachian Indictment Newspaper Clippings, 1959-1970 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Anti-Trust Laws Newspaper Clippings, 1958-1969 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Anti-Semitism Newspaper Clippings, 1966-1979 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - "American Way of Life" Newspaper Clippings, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Anti-Discrimination Legislation Newspaper Clippings, 1965-1967 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Quentin Anderson Newspaper Clipping, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Anderson Papers Newspaper Clippings, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Anarchism Newspaper Clippings, 1964-1968 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Amsterdam Article (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - American Medical Association Article, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    July 30 1949
  - American Labor Research Institute Newspaper Clippings, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - American Jews Miscellaneous Articles, 1959-1964 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - American Committee for Cultural Freedom Newspaper Clippings, 1954-1956 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - American Civilization Article, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    December 23 1960
  - Saul Alinsky Articles, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - "ALIEN" Treaties Senate Record, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Japanese Aliens Newspaper Clippings, 1949-1951 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Aliens Deportation Newspaper Clippings, 1949-1952 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings, 1955-1979 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Last Folder (Box 6, Folder 50)
- Recent accession from MK of current newsletters, etc. (Box 7)
  - New Jersey Law Journal Volume 59, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 1)